<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://seanrioux.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://seanrioux.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-28T11:09:51-05:00</updated><id>https://seanrioux.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Sean Rioux</title><subtitle>I'm a web entrepreneur, programmer, and advocate. I believe in the social potential of a more open and humane world wide web.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Coordinated harmful activity</title><link href="https://seanrioux.com/article/2021-01-28-coordinated-harmful-activity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coordinated harmful activity" /><published>2021-01-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://seanrioux.com/article/coordinated-harmful-activity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://seanrioux.com/article/2021-01-28-coordinated-harmful-activity">&lt;p&gt;Coordinated harmful activity: may refer to technical or socially coordinated platform activity that causes physical, psychological, or informational harm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I research platform manipulation I keep coming across terminology, that as a technologist, I feel it’s important I internalize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linked here is Twitter’s definition. It’s been updated for January 2021, to reflect what we’re seeing play out, internationally (not just in the US) as violent disruptions to civil society continue to be amplified by platforms like theirs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Twitter’s definition is strong, and worth a read. However I can’t help but wonder about the policy response in my own country (Canada). How are we seeking to regulate these platforms to ensure their responsibility to prevent coordinated harmful activity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving it up to mass media and communication platforms to self-regulate is a recipe for failure (it always has been). The US capital was a warning. When the next violent insurrection in a democratic country happens and the finger pointing begins, who will take responsibility for inaction?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Coordinated harmful activity: may refer to technical or socially coordinated platform activity that causes physical, psychological, or informational harm.</summary></entry></feed>